# Anup Vachali

avachali@gmail.com

984 377 0390

Raleigh/Durham, NC

in linkedin.com/in/avachali

### **SKILLS**

## **People and Process:**

Strategy development
Technical Delivery Management
Hiring, Retention and Mentoring
Agile and Waterfall SDLC
Vendor Management

#### **Technical:**

Java, JEE, Spring, Kafka,
Hadoop Ecosystem, Spark,
WebServices, Oracle Service Bus,
JPA, Hibernate, TopLink,
WebLogic, WebSphere,
Oracle, DB2, MongoDB,
MarkLogic, JavaScript, SQL, JUnit,
Maven, Gradle,
Jira, Subversion, Git,
Jenkins Pipelines,
Python and Shell scripts.

#### **EDUCATION**

**MS in Computer Science**University of Memphis,
Memphis, TN

### **SUMMARY**

Accomplished technology leader with experience leading geographically dispersed teams in the design and development of large scale enterprise applications using Java, JEE, Spring and Big Data technologies. Effective collaborator and communicator who can align business and technology teams in fast paced environments to execute on enterprise strategy. Experience in Banking, Insurance and Transportation industries.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## **Asst. Vice President**

October 2017 – Present

Credit Suisse, Raleigh, NC.

- Leading a team of big data engineers to build and maintain a data lake using Hadoop for storing transaction, reference and external data for analytics and business intelligence.
- Architecting a solution to integrate multiple Data Lakes across the company to form a cohesive, one-stop solution for Big Data analytics and reduce data redundancy while increasing speed of onboarding data.
- Successfully led the modernization of a suite of legacy web applications and implemented on a multi-year data strategy plan.
- Collaborated with a team of cross-functional stakeholders in the architecture, design and development of a web based authoring platform for distribution of Research reports.
- Hands on experience with talent development including recruiting and coaching the next generation of leaders in the 'Technical Analyst' and 'Women in Technology' programs. Rolled out an America wide 'Thank you' recognition program to increase employee morale.

#### Sr. Technical Lead

*May 2014 – October 2017* 

MetLife, Raleigh, NC.

- Responsible for development and maintenance of MetLife's Global Sales Platform which is the foundation for Sales and Servicing applications used by MetLife globally.
- Led a technical delivery team in the successful implementation and rollout of the Global Sales platform for the South American market.
- Developed multi-year roadmaps in support of applications for the Group Voluntary and Worksite Benefits organization.
- Led the design and development of critical WebService and Web applications that serve as the backend for MetLife's customer facing portals like MyBenefits and MetOnLine.

# Anup Vachali

Sr. Technical Advisor Sr. Programmer

February 2008 – November 2013 July 2003 – January 2008

FedEx Services, Memphis, TN.

- Architected an Application LifeCycle Management tool suite integrating best-of-breed software tools. This application is used by the global IT organization at FedEx and is the tool for IT compliance.
- Responsible for overall strategy, stakeholder buy-in and leadership of the onsite and offshore development team.
- Led a project to integrate amazon.com with FedEx Tracking. This eliminated redundant infrastructure and increased response time by up to 30%.
- Architect and lead developer of the Notification Delivery System for Tracking and Delivery information. Led a cross organizational group of developers and analysts to design and develop this application.
   Significant achievements include a 300% increase in throughput, 3 million messages a day with negligible backlogs, flexible design to accommodate horizontal scalability and multiple forms of communication and zero downtime in production
- Prototyped Voice Delivery Notification to customers first of its kind in the Transportation industry
- Technical lead for FedExNet, an Enterprise Application Integration project that deals with the movement and translation of data and information exchanged between FedEx and its business partners.
   FedEx saves approximately \$140 million a year in outsourcing and vendor fees